# 这口可以吧 这口可不小
That's a large mouthful of noodles
# 我得好好嚼嚼
I need to chew it carefully
# 葱香 酱油的香
The aroma of scallion and soy sauce
# 干贝的香 香味马上出来了
The aroma of dried scallop. It's coming out fast
# 包括虾的香 真香
And the aroma of shrimp. Smells so good
# 葱油拌面
Scallion oil noodles
# 葱油拌面关键是葱油
The key of scallion oil noodles is the scallion oil
# 两种葱 一个是大葱 和一个小葱
Two kinds of scallions. Spring onion and green onion
# 小葱就是中间那段 碧绿的葱绿
For the green onion, we use the middle section. It's beautifully green
# 然后还有这些蔬菜
And all the vegetables here
# 香菜 小葱根儿 姜丝 洋葱 胡萝卜
Cilantro, green onion stem, shredded ginger, onion, and carrot
# 然后把这个去熬酱油
We use these to prepare the soy sauce
# 还有虾皮呢 虾皮也放在这里面
And shrimp bran? The shrimp bran is also put here
# 今天做的还特别标准
We are cooking in the standard way today
# 今天小黄带着称来的
Today Xiao Huang brought a weigh here
# 酱油大概是在一百五十克
The soy sauce should be about 150 grams
# 多了点 没事儿
A bit more. But it's fine
# 草菇老抽大概是在四百克
Mushroom flavored dark soy sauce is about 400 grams #参考了李锦记的译名
# 然后糖在四十克 不用太甜
And 40 grams of sugar. We don't make it too sweet
# 好这一勺下去差不多了
Ok. Should be enough with this spoon
# 盐大概在七克 它的盐味也够
About 7 grams of salt. It's salty already
# 还要加点水了 水是在一百五十克
And some water. 150 grams of water
# 这个熬好了没关系 可以放在冰箱
It's OK to prepare this much at one time. You can store it
# 可以储存起来
in the fridge
# 把这些料放下去
Let's add these ingredients
# 虾皮起到一个增鲜的作用和增香的作用
The shrimp bran can enhance the savory flavor and the aroma
# 火一烧开了之后就关成小火
Once the liquid starts boiling, turn the heat to a low level
# 熬就可以了 熬十五分钟
Boil it slowly. Boil for 15 minutes
# 然后接下来我们就把虾干用温水泡
Then we soak the dried shrimps in warm water
# 泡个五到八分钟就可以了
Soak for about 5 to 8 minutes
# 干贝也得泡吧 干贝提前泡好的
-Do we need to soak the dried scallop as well? -It's soaked in advance
# 泡好了之后得把它搓成丝
After soaking, you need to rub it into thin fibers
# 待会我帮你搓吧 谢谢师父
-Let me do it for you later. -Thanks, master
# 然后我们这边一烧开了之后
As soon as it starts boiling
# 大家一定要看好时间
You must be careful of the time
# 不能超过十五分钟 超过十五分钟之后
You shouldn't boil it for more than 15 minutes. Otherwise,
# 因为酱油 盐味本身还有盐
Because there's already salt in soy sauce
# 它会越做越咸
It'll become saltier and saltier
# 照一下我得把这干贝给它揉碎
Please film this. I'm rubbing the dried scallop
# 这干贝泡透以后俩手一揉
Rub the fully soaked dried scallop with two hands
# 没事待会再揉 还得揉一遍 特别细
Don't worry. I'm gonna rub it again later to make it thin enough
# 就跟一首歌唱的似的
Just like in the song
# 我的心一揉就碎了
'My heart breaks as you rub it'
# 你看碎了吧 对碎了
-See? It's broken into pieces. -Yes
# 烧开了之后就一定是关成小火加盖
When it starts boiling, you must use low heat and close the lid
# 我们把它挪那边来
Let's move it here
# 十五分钟大家看好时间
15 minutes. Be careful of the time!
# 锅里面我们加油炼葱油 花生油
Let's add some oil into the wok to prepare the scallion oil. We use peanut oil here
# 先把大葱放下去
Add the spring onion first
# 不用油特别热是吧 对不用油特别热
-We don't need to use hot oil here, right? -No
# 慢慢的熬慢慢的炸就行
Just soak-fry it slowly
# 火也不用太大 葱的香味完全炸出来
We don't need to use high heat either. The aroma of scallions should be brought out completely
# 炸这不能急
You shouldn't be impatient while frying this
# 炸的有一点点上色了有一点点干了
When the scallion becomes a bit darker and drier
# 葱还得要呢
We'll need to use the fried spring onion later
# 所以这葱切的要漂亮
So you should cut it nicely
# 然后我们就把小葱（放进去）
Then we add the green onion (into the wok)
# 不能切太长也不能切太短
You should cut it into a proper length. Not too long, nor too short
# 这个放下去慢慢的炸一下
Fry it slowly
# 大家看一下这个葱稍微有一点发黄
See? When the green onion just turns yellow
# 然后把这个火关了
Stop heating
# 用余温把它沁一下 就可以了
Soak-fry the green onion with the residual heat and it's done
# 这样的话保持葱的绿色
In this way, the green color can be preserved
# 而且它的香味还出来了
While the aroma is brought out
# 把它捞出来
Take it out
# 这个油倒出来
Now pour out the oil
# 这个锅就留油不用洗了
Keep some oil in the wok. You don't need to wash it
# 然后就炸干贝丝了
Then we fry the dried scallop
# 葱油放在旁边备用
Let's put aside the scallion oil
# 这面要不好吃的才怪呢
The noodles can't taste bad
# 花生油 有三两
Peanut oil. That's about 150 grams
# 油温稍微低一点 慢慢撒下去
Use a low oil temperature. Sprinkle it slowly
# 大家拿不准的话可以先少放一点点
If you are not sure (about the temperature), add a bit first
# 慢慢的试 稍微再等一会 慢慢放
Try it slowly. Wait for a while and add some more
# 两成油温 慢慢的撒下去
20% hot (60 degrees Celcius). Sprinkle it slowly
# 干贝炸好了之后放在冰箱里面
When the dried scallop is ready, store it in the fridge
# 拌小凉菜 拌面的时候放一点点
So that you can use some when making a cold dish or cooking noodles
# 这个干贝把它搓碎了之后
When the dried scallop is rubbed into pieces
# 不要一起下得慢慢的下
Don't add it altogether. Add it slowly
# 一起放下去它容易起坨
It tends to clump up if you add it all together
# 不要炸得太干太硬 金黄色
Don't fry it too dry and hard. When it's golden yellow (it's done)
# 干贝的香味马上出来了
The aroma of the dried scallop is coming out now
# 这个不需要吸油
Here we don't need to absorb the oil
# 葱油拌面本身也需要油 又一份油
-Because you need oil in this dish. -Another portion of oil
# 然后这个虾把它剥一下就行
The dried shrimp... Simply peel it
# 剥去虾的外皮  每个细节都很重要
Remove the shrimp shell. Each detail matters
# 这个不能炸 一定要煎
You shouldn't deep fry the shrimp. Fry it with less oil
# 锅里面少放一点点油
Add a little oil into the wok
# 就是刚刚炸干贝的油
Just the oil that we used for frying the dried scallop
# 鲜上加鲜 火小一点点
-There's a double savory taste! -Use low heat
# 煎一分钟就可以了
Fry it for just one minute
# 因为本身干虾可以直接吃
Because the dried shrimp itself is ready to eat
# 把它两面煎成微微的黄色
Fry both sides into pale yellow
# 把这虾的香味煎出来就可以了
Fry out the aroma of the shrimp
# 这干虾家市场能买到么 市场能买到
-Can we find the dried shrimp in the markets? -Yes
# 没有干贝 没有虾干
If you don't have dried scallop or dried shrimp
# 用点海米我觉得也行 也可以
-I think you can use 'Hai mi' (small dried shrimp) instead. -Yes, that also works
# 拣出来 一会拌面的时候
Take the shrimp out. When we make the noodles later
# 把它放上去就可以了
Put the shrimps on the top
# 得关了火了 你看熬出来了
Now we turn off the heat. See? The soy sauce is ready
# 蔬菜的香味完全出来了
The aroma of vegetables is fully coming out
# 接下来我们就把酱油箅出来
Then we filter the soy sauce
# 烧水煮面了 好勒
Now boil the noodles. Ok!
# 碱面么 南方用碱面 北方用细面也可以
-Noodles made with soda? -You can buy noodles with soda in southern areas. But if you are in the north, you may use normal thin noodles
# 这个下去煮不能超过两分钟
You shouldn't boil the noodles for over 2 minutes
# 如果时间煮久了面会坨 没有面的筋道
If too long, the noodles will stick together and lose the chewy texture
# 不能超过两分钟 大家一定要注意了
No longer than two minutes! Be careful
# 捞起来一个简单的技巧
There's a simple trick when you take the noodles out
# 大家看一下 过一下凉
Take a look. Cool it down with running water
# 冲凉 沥一下水
Cool down with cold water and drain it
# 然后放到锅里面一烫
Then heat it shortly again in the pot
# 这样拌面的时候它就一点都不坨
In this way, the noodles won't be sticky at all
# 把水沥干
Drain the water
# 二两多面 酱油应该在十几克
That's about 100 grams of noodles, so we add about 10 grams of soy sauce
# 根据个人的一个口味
Depending on your preference
# 少放一点点 拌下去
Don't add too much. Stir the noodles
# 颜色红 颜色红亮
-The color is red. -Red and shiny
# 炸好的葱油 基本上是一勺就可以了
Scallion oil. One spoon is enough
# 再来一点更香一点
Add a bit more. It'll smell better
# 闻一下师父
Smell it, master
# 来师叔您也闻一下
Shi shu (junior master), smell it
# 葱油味真香
The scallion oil smells great
# 手看到没有 卷一下回一下
Watch this. Roll it forth and back
# 大家看一下
Take a look at this
# 炸好的干葱 放在里面 来一点点
Fried scallion. Put some on the top
# 炸好的干贝 多来一点
Fried dried scallop. A bit more
# 虾干 好嘞
Dried shrimp. Done
# 干贝海鲜葱油拌面 好了
Scallion oil noodles with dried scallop and seafood. Ready to serve!
# 二伯 先尝 把这机子给我
Er Bai, take a bite first. Pass me the camera
# 香不香 他这个料配的太好了
-Is it delicious? -His recipe is marvelous
# 面条的筋道劲儿也有
The noodles are chewy enough
# 虾 瑶柱提的鲜味  全融在这面边了
The savory tastes of shrimp and dried scallop all fuse with the noodles
# 我一碗不够吃的 一会儿你再来一碗
-One bowl like this is not enough for me. -You can have one more later
# 回头再给您煮一碗
Let me make one more serving for you later
# 太香了 大爷别光我吃
So delicious. I'm not eating alone, Da Ye
# 这口可以吧 这口可不小
That's a large mouthful of noodles
# 我的天这口全塞进去了
Wow. You had it all
# 我得好好嚼嚼
I need to chew it carefully
# 您这嘴都倒不开了
You can't turn it over in your mouth
# 真香 葱香 酱油的香
Tastes so good. The aroma of scallion, soy sauce
# 干贝的香 包括虾的香
Dried scallop, and shrimp
# 还一香呢 面条的香 香到家了
-There's one more. The aroma of noodles. -Ultimately aromatic!
# 我不管了我现在得来一碗了
Forget about the shooting. Let me have one more bowl of noodles
# 好吃啊 好吃
So delicious!
# 那天是最有收获
I earned the most on that day
# 拿回120块钱来
I brought back 120 yuan
# 那是没有大票
At that time, there was no high denomination banknote
# 全10块钱一张的
The highest was 10 yuan
# 我在我们财务换了12张
I exchanged 12 banknotes at our accounts office
# 特别新的新票
The newest banknotes. Freshly made
# 回到家里头以后
When I went back home
# 往桌上一放
I put the money on the table
# 跟大妈一说 我说看看
And I told Da Ma that, 'Look'
# 这是咱俩
'This is the money...'
# 省吃俭用一个一年
'that we cannot save'
# 也挣不到的
'even if we live frugally for a whole year'
# 120块钱
'120 yuan'
# 我一个月就拿回来了
'I earned these within one month'
# 想吃什么好吃的买
'If you want to eat anything decent, buy it!'
# 大妈当时说什么
What did Da Ma say?
# 她也挺激动的
She was also excited
# 你想我一个月利用我的公休
Think about it. In that month, I made use of my holidays
# 那时候休息一天
I had one day off each week at that time
# 我休息也就上外边干活
But I also worked outside on that day
# 第2个月的时候
In the second month
# 人家学校通知我
The school informed me
# 还车接车送
Initially, they picked me up and sent me back in a car
# 就通知我不车接车送了
The school informed me that they wouldn't send a car for me anymore
# 一天给五十块钱
But my salary was increased to 50 yuan per day
# 我更高兴了
I was even more happy
# 我为了省三毛五分钱
To save the 0.35 yuan commuting expense
# 我从王府井骑到动物园
I rode a bike from Wang Fu Jing to Beijing Zoo
# 然后那边再坐一段公交车
Then took the bus from there
# 一直到颐和园
To the Summer Palace
# 中央党校在颐和园
That's where the Party School of the Central Committee of CPC was
# 我就很早就起来了
So I got up very early
# 然后8:30必须到学校
As I had to arrive at the school at 8:30 am
# 一个月拿回来200块钱
In that month, I earned 200 yuan
# 我就觉得我太神了
I felt great about myself
# 我说咱家不缺钱
I was like, 'We do not lack money now!'
# 那时候一说回家
At that time, when we visited our families
# 给双方的父母
We used to send our parents
# 给拿20
20 yuan
# 那边拿20
For both mine and hers
# 都买点好吃的
We bought them some decent food
# 很骄傲
You must be very proud
# 特别骄傲
Yes. Very proud
# 我们酒店里边有个小卖部
There was a shop in my restaurant
# 卖进口的香蕉
that sold imported bananas
# 特别大
They were extremely large
# 那阵市场没有啊
There was no banana in the markets
# 五毛六一斤
The price was 0.56 yuan per jin (1.12 yuan/kg)
# 一般人还买不起
Most people could not afford it
# 来了以后呢一说卖香蕉
When I went to the shop and wanted to buy some bananas
# 我还纳闷了
I was wondering
# 我说卖水果的这还准备一把刀啊
Why they needed a knife to sell bananas
# 闹了半天是什么
But it turned out that
# 买香蕉来三根
People only bought, like 3 bananas at a time
# 有时候人家可能买五根
Sometimes maybe 5 bananas (so they needed to cut a whole bunch bananas)
# 我有钱了
But I was rich
# 是吧
Right?
# 把那把香蕉全给给我约上
I was like, 'I'll take all that bunch of bananas!'
# 人家都很纳闷
The clerks were all surprised
# 一把香蕉
The whole bunch of bananas
# 一约五斤
was 5 jin (2.5 kg)
# 2块8毛钱
It was 2.8 yuan
# 2块8毛钱那就半个月的生活费了
2.8 yuan was the total life expense of half a month
# 别人家半个月生活费
In common families
# 提着一把香蕉回家的时候
When I came home with a bunch of bananas
# 在路面上回头率极高
Everyone was looking at me
# 有面子
It was so graceful
# 然后卖那个橘子
I also bought some oranges
# 6月份卖橘子
It was in June
# 市场根本就没有卖橘子的
There was no orange in the markets at all
# 那时候北京饭店还是比较特殊
Beijing Hotel was somewhat a special place then
# 4毛8一斤
It sold oranges, but the price was 0.48 yuan/jin (0.96 yuan/kg)
# 来5斤
I bought 5 jin of oranges (2.5 kg)
# 搁在网兜里边
They were put in a net pocket
# 装在那塑料袋里头
inside a plastic bag
# 骑自行车
I was riding my bike
# 回头率极高
Still, I was attracting a lot of attention
# 那不是看我 都是看橘子
But they were not actually looking at me, but the oranges
# 我觉得我特别的自豪
I felt so proud
# 一来二去我就
As time went by
# 第一锻炼了我的厨艺
I improved my cooking skills
# 丰富了我的知识
and learned more knowledge
# 后来我就下决心
Later on, I made my decision
# 一定要好好上学
that I must continue my study
# 我也要完成我的一个愿望
I also wanted to realize my dream
# 我说我一定要找机会
I decided that I must find a chance
# 要上一大学
to study in a college
# 99年的时候
In 1999
# 我就报考了北京教育学院
I applied to Beijing Institute of Education
# 这个烹饪系
Department of cooking
# 报了一个大专
So I went to a college
# 在两三年当中
During the 2 or 3 years
# 我学了不少知识
I learnt a lot of knowledge
# 因为我觉得我
Becuase I felt that
# 在理论上
in terms of theory
# 缺口太大了
I had a lot of shortcomings
# 应该在理论上好好丰富一下
So I should enrich my knowledge about cooking theories
# 到八四年
It was not until 1984
# 市面上开始有烹饪书了
that cooking books began to appear in the stores
# 我就下决心
I also made my mind
# 是吧
that
# 只要我发现一本烹饪书
as long as I find a new cooking book
# 见一本买一本
I would buy it
# 我又到现在
Up to now
# 我储存了将近小五百本
I've bought about 500 cooking books
# 那个年代出的书
published at that time
# 那您家都成一小图书馆了
Then your home almost becomes a small library
# 我有将近5个书柜
I have about 5 bookcases
# 全是我这是存的书
that are full of the books I bought then
# 这个书对我帮助太大了
The books helped me a lot
# 是吧
Right?
# 也丰富了很多知识
My knowledge was tremendously enriched
# 因为我跟二伯不太一样
My experience was different from Er Bai
# 二伯是专业学校毕业
Er Bai graduated from a professional school
# 他在服务学校毕业
A professional school of service
# 我没有上过这个
But I didn't go to that school
# 没有机会
I didn't have a chance
# 我直接从初中来到酒店
I started working at a restaurant after graduating from a middle school
# 对理论上我加以很大的研究
So I spent a lot of time on studying cooking theories
# 凡是我不懂的
Once I didn't understand something
# 看书
I went to the books for an answer
# 某一环节不知道的
If I didn't know about some step
# 我就有时候去寻找到书店寻找
Sometimes I searched for the answer in bookstores
# 另外还有
What's more
# 我们出了很多烹饪辞典
There were a lot of cooking dictionaries
# 还有中国烹饪百科全书
and The Encyclopedia of Chinese Cooking
# 上面有很多知识
There was much knowledge in these books
# 我就搜索
So I looked through them
# 搜索呢
Apart from just looking through the books
# 我又增加我的印象
I needed to have better impressions (of the knowledge)
# 怎么办
But how?
# 记笔记
I took notes
# 所以记笔记这个习惯
So my habit of taking notes
# 是我多年养成的一个好的习惯
is a good habit that I had for many years
# 感觉您特别能吃苦
I can feel that you could endure a lot of hardships
# 也能吃苦
Yes
# 确实是
Indeed
# 然后我这个工作了一年
In that year
# 就是外边干活干了一年
I mean, when I had my part-time job outside
# 你猜我挣多少钱
Guess how much money I made?